Caso March papers, Inclusive: 1927-1985, undated Bulk: 1946-1950
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
Caso March papers
Inclusive: 1927-1985, undated Bulk: 1946-1950
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
15
March, Caso, 1911 - 1985
8 document boxes 5 oversize boxes
The Caso March Papers contain scrapbooks, personal files, news clippings, campaign materials, photographs, and oversize diagrams. These materials document his three unsuccessful attempts for governor, as well as his personal life and career.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Caso March was born March 9, 1911, in Saginaw, Texas. He was a graduate of North Side High School in Fort Worth, Texas, and completed bachelors, masters, and law degrees at Baylor University in Waco, Texas. After graduating from Baylor, March was employed by the Federal Power Commission in Washington, DC from 1934-1942. While in Washington, March earned an additional master’s of law and doctorate in judicial science at the American University and National University, respectively.
In 1942, March enlisted in the Army during World War II. He served as an infantry officer, primarily in Southeast Asia. After his service, March and his family moved to Waco. During this time March began work as a faculty member in the Baylor School of Law and completed his first campaign for governor of Texas.
Caso March was a perpetual candidate for Texas Governor. He ran unsuccessfully in 1946, 1948, and 1950, once using the slogan “For every man, a tax-free home.” Prior to the 1950 election, he resigned his post at Baylor to pursue the campaign full time. Without a win, March returned to a career as an attorney for the National Labor Relations Board.
Caso March was married to the former Hattie Mae Yelvington and had two children, Ben and Ann.
Scope and Content
The papers of Caso March include personal files, news clippings, photographs, scrapbooks, and several large diagrams from March’s time with the Federal Power Commission.
Most of the materials are dated circa 1930-1950, and trace March’s course from college at Baylor University through his three runs for governor of Texas in 1946, 1948, and 1950. Items from his high school days in Fort Worth, Texas, are also present. March’s time with the Federal Power Commission, 1934-1942, his service in the military during World War II, 1943-1945, at Baylor as a law professor, 1946-1948, and campaign materials from his races and other political campaigns of the late 1940s and early 1950s are also present.
The personal files contain mostly business, family, and campaign correspondence. Family correspondence is well represented with his wife Hattie Mae, amid their courtship during World War II and beyond. Also included are news clippings, scrapbooks, and limited photographs.
Arrangement
An inventory was compiled in 2006 which included four series with many detailed subseries. Subseries have been consolidated and an additional series has been added. The current arrangement includes five series: Campaigns, Correspondence, Federal Power Commission, Personal, and Audio-Visual. The Campaigns series is further divided into General, Speeches, and Other Politicians; the Federal Power Commission series is divided into Correspondence, Newsletters and News clippings, and Notes and Official Documents; and the Personal series is divided into General, Clippings, Correspondence, Education, and Photographs and Scrapbooks.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 15. Acquired 2005-03-01
Related Resources
Related references
“Caso March.” Star Telegram (Fort Worth, TX), May 15, 1985.
“Ex-BU Professor Caso March Dies.” Waco Tribune-Herald (Waco, TX), May 13, 1985.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
March, Caso, 1911-1985.
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University. Law School.; Baylor University.; United States. Federal Power Commission.
Subjects
College teachers -- Texas -- Waco.; Governors--Election.; Lawyers.; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States.
Genres
Albums (Books); Business correspondence.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Maps.; Newsletters.; Personal correspondence.; Phonograph records; Photographs.; Programs (Publications).; Records (Documents); Speeches.
- Campaigns, 1931-1950, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Campaigns series documents the three gubernatorial races in which Caso March took part; 1946, 1948, and 1950. The series is divided into three subseries: General, Speeches, and Other Politicians. Materials include campaign advertisements, speeches given by or on behalf of March, and items related to politicians March spoke for or ran against. This series is dated 1931-1950, and is in good condition.
  The General subseries documents March’s races and includes brochures, newsletters, stationery, signs, expense reports, and various campaign records. Dated 1938-1950, this subseries is arranged chronologically.
  The Speeches subseries is dated 1946-1950, and arranged chronologically. Transcripts from all three campaigns are present, including radio addresses, stump speeches, and press releases. March ran on the platform of fewer taxes which is the main topic of most speeches.
  The Other Politicians subseries focuses less on Caso March and more on his opponents, which included Beauford Jester, Jerry Saddler, Grover Sellers, and John Lee Smith. Materials from State Attorney General Price Daniel and Preston Weatherbed are also present. Notably, March was an active orator while attending Baylor. In 1934, he gave endorsement speeches on behalf of Tom Hunter who was opposing Ross Shaw Sterling. Materials include news clippings, advertisements, flyers, mailing lists, and speeches. This subseries is arranged chronologically from 1931-1950.
  - General, 1938-1950, undated; 1
    - Advertisements, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Envelopes, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letterhead, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Poster, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Texas map, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Campaign Notes, 1938-1948 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Flyers, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Metal Printing Plate, circa 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Resignation, circa 1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - American Legion Rally Program, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Democratic Chair Speech, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Expense reports, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Flyers, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Newsletter, “The Tattler”, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Newspaper Advertisement, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Voter’s Guides, League of Women Voters, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Rural Traffic Safety Photographs, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Texas/New Mexico Map, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Speeches, 1946-1950, undated; 2
    - Speaking Schedules, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - “Booze and Barnyard Morals,” draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - General, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Taxes, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Taxes and Expenditures, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Taxes, Railroads, drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Veterans Endorsement message, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Veterans, Pensions, Teachers, circa 1946 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Taxes, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Tom F. Hunter, 1948 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Taxes, 1948 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Electricity, Power, drafts, circa 1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Oil and Gas, Pensions, Teachers, drafts, circa 1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Tax-Free Home, 1950 January 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Gilmer-Aikin Bill, 1950 March 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Texas State Network Broadcast, 1950 May 15 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Eagles State Convention, Galveston, 1950 May 20 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Courthouse Square, Waco, TX, 1950 June 12 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - WFAA Broadcast, Marine Park, Fort Worth, Texas, 1950 July 21 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - KPRC, WFAA Radio Broadcasts, 1950 October 31 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Other Politicians, 1931-1950, undated; 3
    - Judge Harry N. Graves, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Jerry Sadler, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Tom Hunter, Ross Sterling, 1931-1934 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - O. H. Cross, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - W.D. McFarlane, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Ed Gossett, Earl Earp, Walter M. Pierce, Pearl Smith, Walter Woodul, 1938-1941 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - John E. Rankin, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Grover Sellers, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - John Lee Smith, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Beauford Jester, 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - F. G. Swanson, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Price Daniel, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Cyclone Davis, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Preston Weatherred, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Correspondence, 1936-1950; 2
  The Correspondence series is dated 1936-1950. Included are general correspondence with several politicians, representatives, and congressmen addressing March’s search for a legal position in Washington, D.C. Also included is personal correspondence with the Democratic Party, Tom Hunter, and others during his campaigns. Notable names within this series are Tom Hunter, Olin “Tiger” Teague, and Cyclone Davis. This series is in good condition.
  - General (1 of 2), 1936 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - General (2 of 2), 1936 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - General, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Representatives and Congressmen, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - General, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - General, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - General, 1946 January-March (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General, 1946 April (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General, 1946 May (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - General, 1946 June (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - General, 1946 July (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - General, 1946 August-October (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Richard B. Humphrey, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - General, 1948 January-April (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - General, 1948 May (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - “Un-Texan” Responses, 1948 June (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - General, 1948 June (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - General, 1948 July (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - General, Tax Records, 1948 August-December (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Natural Gas, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - General, 1950 January-May (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - General, 1950 June (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - General, 1950 July (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - General, 1950 August-September (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Federal Power Commission, 1935-1946, undated; 3
  The Federal Power Commission (FPC) Series is dated 1924-1942, and covers the time Caso March was employed by the FPC as an attorney in Washington, D.C. from 1934-1942. During this time March produced correspondence, collected news clippings and newsletters, and created notes and official documents. Many of his dealings were with the Niagara Falls Power Company and his case to prove it constituted a monopoly. This series is in good condition.
  The Correspondence subseries consists of letters of recommendation from members of Congress in support of March’s application as attorney at the Federal Power Commission. Also included are notifications received while employed and other general correspondence. This subseries is dated 1934-1942.
  The Newsletters and News clippings subseries documents relevant issues to the Commission during March’s tenure. The clippings and newsletters refer to March’s role in the Niagara Falls Power Hearing. Also included is a scrapbook with additional clippings and references to a chart created by March which became highly controversial. A research copy has been made of the scrapbook. This subseries is dated 1939-1941.
  The Notes and Official Documents series includes work related notes and meeting agendas during March’s time at the Federal Power Commission. Also included are copies of a chart created by March in attempts to describe the Niagara Falls Power Commission as a monopoly. This subseries is dated 1935-1946.
  - Correspondence, 1934-1942; 1
    - Appointment to Federal Power Commission, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Appointment to Federal Power Commission, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Salary Information and Raises, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Raise Notification, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Labor Magazine, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - General, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - General, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Newsletters and News clippings, 1939-1941; 2
    - Federal Power Commission Daily News Digest, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Federal Power Commission Scrapbook (copy), 1939 (Box 9 OVZ, Folder 1)
    - Federal Power Commission Scrapbook (original), 1939 (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 1)
    - Federal Power Commission Daily News Digest, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Federal Power Commission Daily News Digest, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Federal Power Commission Daily News Digest, 1942 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Federal Power Commission Newsletter, 1946 March (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - News Clippings, Niagara Falls Power Company, 1937-1941 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Notes and Official Documents, 1935-1946, undated; 3
    - Niagara Falls Power Commission Charts (1 of 3), undated (Box 11 OVZ, Folder 1)
    - Niagara Falls Power Commission Charts (2 of 3), undated (Box 12 OVZ, Folder 1)
    - Niagara Falls Power Commission Charts (3 of 3), undated (Box 13 OVZ, Folder 1)
    - Proposals and Memorandums, 1935-1941 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Proposals and Memorandums, 1935-1942 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Proposals and Memorandums, 1940-1946 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Notes, Paperwork, Circa 1946 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Personal, 1927-1985, undated; 4
  The Personal series documents different stages of Caso March’s life. This series is divided into five subseries: General, Clippings, Correspondence, Education, and Photographs and Scrapbooks. Items present include biographical materials, Boy Scout papers, family correspondence, organizational handouts, class notes, military records, news clippings, and photographs. The series is dated 1920-1985, arranged chronologically with each subseries, and in good condition.
  The General subseries is dated 1927-1985, and includes biographical materials, obituaries, Boy Scout and Military Records, newsletters, personal notes including business cards and contact information, and reproduction monetary notes. This subseries is arranged chronologically.
  The Clippings subseries is dated 1942-1950, and covers a variety of topics including March’s campaigns. Also mentioned is the visit by President Harry S Truman to Waco. In a previous inventory, several newspapers documenting this occasion were present. However, due to their condition, the papers have been removed from the physical collection and reside online at: digitalcollections.baylor.edu.
  The Correspondence subseries is dated 1920-1940. Items include letters from Caso March to his wife Hattie Mae. These take place prior to their marriage, during his military service, while in Washington, D.C., and while campaigning. Also included are letters to and from extended family. This subseries is organized chronologically.
  The Education subseries documents March’s time both as a student and professor. Early materials, such as handbooks and rosters, are representative of his time in high school. Class notes, organizational items, and small memorabilia note his participation while attending Baylor. Also included are examinations, handbooks, and notes from his time as a Baylor Law professor. This subseries is organized chronologically from 1927-1949.
  The Photographs and Scrapbooks subseries holds general postcards, illustrations, and photographs. Also included is a political cartoons scrapbook from March’s childhood as well as a scrapbook with certificates and awards earned as an adolescent. A research copy has been created for this scrapbook. The subseries is dated 1924-1932, however most items are undated. It is arranged chronologically and in average condition.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photographic print; Postcards
  - General, 1927-1985, undated; 1
    - Committee Files, Waco Reception for President Truman, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Reproduction Confederate States Currency, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Tax stubs, Business cards and short notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Notes and Programs, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - H.B. 586 and H.B. 87, Public Utilities, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Boy Scout Attendance and Dues Records, circa 1927 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Boy Scout Constitution and By-Laws, circa 1927 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Boy Scout Log Sheets and Applications, circa 1927 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Boy Scout Transfer and Membership Records, circa 1927 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Boy Scout Enrollment Papers and Certificates, 1927 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Boy Scout Individual Scout Records, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Boy Scout Monthly Troop Reports, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Boy Scout Newsletters, 1927 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Pentworth Baptist Church Newsletters and Sunday School Programs, 1941-1942 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Military records, 1942-1945 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Newsletter, Southern Baptist Convention Bulletin, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Newsletter, The Emancipator, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Obituaries, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1942-1950; 2
    - Gas Inquiry, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - General (1 of 2), 1946 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - General (2 of 2), 1946 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - General, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - General (1 of 2), 1948 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - General (2 of 2), 1948 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - General, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - General, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1920-1940; 3
    - Letters to and from family, 1920-1940 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Friends, Family, and Colleagues, 1930-1933 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Friends, Family, and Colleagues, 1931-1934 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Letters to and from family, 1933-1945 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Job Application Endorsement Requests, 1934 January-July (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Job Application Endorsement Requests, 1934 September-December (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Job Application Endorsement Requests, 1935 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Education, 1927-1949, undated; 4
    - Baylor Class Notecards (1 of 2), undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Baylor Class Notecards (2 of 2), undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - “Tidings from the Baylor Towers” booklet, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Debater’s Handbook and Bulletins, 1927-1928 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - R.O.T.C. Roster, Personal Notes, 1927-1928 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Pi Kappa Delta Fraternity Convention Booklets, 1928-1932 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Baylor Songs and Yells Book (MISSING), circa 1929 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Baylor Sticker, circa 1929 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Class and Personal Notes, Baylor, 1929-1934 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Economics Booklet, Commencement Programs, 1931-1932 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - “High School Time Saver” Manual, North Fort Worth Senior High School, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Baylor Law Exams, 1933 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Baylor Commencement Announcement, 1934 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Baylor Homecoming Clippings, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - The Baylor Bulletin, Law Number, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Baylor Law Professor, General, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1924-1932, undated; 5
    - General Photographs and Postcards, undated (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Poetry and Political Cartoons Scrapbook, undated (Box 9 OVZ, Folder 2)
    - Certificates and Clippings Scrapbook (copy), 1924-1932 (Box 9 OVZ, Folder 3)
    - Certificates and Clippings Scrapbook (original), 1924-1932 (Box 10 OVZ, Folder 2)
- Audio-Visual, 1948, undated; 5
  General condition: Average.
  The Audio-Visual series is dated 1948, during March’s second campaign for Governor. These vinyl records contain audio files of March speaking on several occasions. One of the records includes an introduction by Pat Neff. These are in average condition.
  Phonodisc
  - “Presto” record, undated (Box 9 OVZ, Folder 4)
  - “Caso March, Dixie Net”, 1948 June 9 (Box 9 OVZ, Folder 5)
  - “Pat Neff Introducing Caso March”, 1948 June 24 (Box 9 OVZ, Folder 6)